<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                      "file:///usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.5/docbookx.dtd
"
>
<book>
    <bookinfo>
      <title>VMUSBSpecTcl</title>
      <author><firstname>Ron</firstname><surname>Fox</surname></author>
      <revhistory>
          <revision>
             <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
             <date>May 18, 1012</date>
             <authorinitials>RF</authorinitials>
             <revremark>Original Release</revremark>
          </revision>
      </revhistory>
    </bookinfo>
    <chapter>
        <title>Introduction and background</title>
        <para>
            VMUSBSpecTcl is a tailored SpecTcl which has unpacking software
            for all of the modules supported by the VMUSBReadout program.
            By inserting a bit of  metadata in the DAQ configuration file
            used by VMUSBReadout, you can use VMUSBSpecTcl to analyze data
            read by VMUSBReadout producing and produce raw spectra without
            writing a single line of code.
        </para>
        <para>
            The remainder of this manual has the following chapters:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>VMUSBSpecTcl configuration</emphasis> describes
                    what you need to put in the daq configuration file to
                    make VMUSBSpecTcl create parameters and raw spectra for
                    each of the devices in your readout.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>Extending VMUSBSpecTcl</emphasis> describes
                    how to extend the base VMUSBSpecTcl application.
                    At this poit in time emphasis is on how to add
                    additional event processors that interact with the raw,
                    unpacked parameters to produce computed parameters.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                <emphasis>Running VMUSBSpecTcl</emphasis> describes what you need
                to do to run VMUSBSpecTcl
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>Reference information</emphasis> provides manpage
                    like documntation to soem of the bits and pieces of
                    VMUSBSpecTcl that need it.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
                
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>VMUSBSpecTcl  configuration</title>
        <para>
            VMUSBReadout uses a Tcl configuration file to define and configure
            devices in the VME crate and to select the order in which they
            are read out for each stack.
        </para>
        <para>
            Normally one has a primary event stack and a scaler stack however,
            the hardware, and software, support a total of 8 stacks with
            differing trigger conditions including front panel, timed and
            VME interrupts.
        </para>
        <para>
            By adding a small amount of metadata to the configuration file,
            the same information can be used by SpecTcl to select the order in
            which it runs unpacking objects that understand the format of data
            from each module, and distribute data from each channel into
            parameters.  Furthermore, once those raw parameters are known, the
            SpecTcl configuration processing creates raw spectra for each
            parameter that has been defined.
        </para>
        <para>
            The primary bit of metadata required by VMUSBSpecTcl is  Tcl array
            named <varname>adcChannels</varname>.  This array is indexed by
            module name  and each element contains a list of the parameter names
            to be associated with the input channels of the digitizer.
            If a channel is unused, use an empty string (<literal>""</literal>).
            If the last several channels are unused you can just supply a shorter
            list.
        </para>
        <para>
            The remainder of this chapter are a set of examples that
            show how you can define the parameters of a CAEN V785 peak
            sensing ADC module you have named <literal>adc</literal>.
            The first example shows how to use a Tcl loop to define
            parameters named <literal>adc.00</literal> through
            <literal>adc.31</literal>.  The Tcl
            <command>format</command> command is used to ensure that
            the channel number has leading zeroes if needed.
            <command>lappend</command> (list append)
            is used to construct the list an element
            at a time each pass through the loop.
        </para>
        <example>
            <title>Using a loop to create parameters</title>
            <programlisting>
for {set i 0} {$i &lt; 32} {incr i} {
    lappend adcChannels(adc) [format adc.%02d $i]
}
            </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
            The next example equivalent to the previous one but much more
            work to write.  Something like this may be needed, however if your
            parameter names don't occur in sets with some regular pattern
            (remember that you could have several for or foreach loops all
            lappending to the same <varname>adcChannels</varname> element).
        </para>
        <example>
            <title>Creating parameter names the long way</title>
            <programlisting>
set adcChannels(adc) [list adc.00 adc.01 adc.02 adc.03 adc.04 \
                             adc.05 adc.06 adc.07 adc.08 adc.09 \
                             adc.10 adc.11 adc.12 adc.13 adc.14 \
                             adc.15 adc.16 adc.17 adc.18 adc.19 \
                             adc.20 adc.21 adc.22 adc.23 adc.24 \
                             adc.25 adc.26 adc.27 adc.28 adc.29 \
                             adc.30 adc.31                      \
                        ]
            </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
            The next example shows how to declare define the same ADC, if you
            are not using channels 5 through 9.
        </para>
        <example>
            <title>Unused parameters in the middle</title>
            <programlisting>
set adcChannels(adc) [list adc.00 adc.01 adc.02 adc.03 adc.04 \
                             ""     ""     ""     ""     ""     \
                             adc.10 adc.11 adc.12 adc.13 adc.14 \
                             adc.15 adc.16 adc.17 adc.18 adc.19 \
                             adc.20 adc.21 adc.22 adc.23 adc.24 \
                             adc.25 adc.26 adc.27 adc.28 adc.29 \
                             adc.30 adc.31                      \
                        ]
            </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
            Finally, if you are only using the first 8 channels of the
            ADC (channels 0-7):
        </para>
        <example>
            <title>Onl using the first few channels</title>
            <programlisting>
for {set i 0} {$i &lt; 8} {incr i} {
    lappend adcChannels(adc) [format adc.%02d $i]
}
            </programlisting>
        </example>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Extending VMUSBSpecTcl</title>
        <para>
            In this chapter we will learn how to extend VMUSBSpecTcl by adding
            event processors that produce computed parameters from existing
            raw parameters prepared for us by the VMUSBSpecTcl raw event processor.
            The specific learning objectives are:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Learn how to get a copy of the VMUSBSpecTcl skeleton.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Learn how to locate and reference parameters by name using the
                    Spectcl API.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Learn how to create a Tree parameter proxy for a named
                    parameter.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Learn how to integrate our changes with the skelton.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Copying the VMUSBSpecTcl skeleton</title>
            <para>
                The VMUSBSpecTcl skeleton is located in
                <filename>$SpecTclHome/VMUSBSkel</filename> where
                <literal>$SpecTclHome</literal> is the top level directory
                of your SpecTcl installation.  For version 3.3 at the
                NSCL, this is <filename>/usr/opt/spectcl/3.3/VMUSBSkel</filename>.
                <footnote>
                    <para>VMUSB support first appears in version
                    3.3-009.  Be sure your SpecTcl version is at least this
                    high before looking.
                    </para></footnote>
            </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para>
            If The following sequence of commands creates an empty directory
            and copies the skeleton files into it from
            <filename>/usr/opt/spectcl/3.3/VMUSBSkel</filename>:
        </para>
        <example>
            <title>Copying the skeleton files</title>
            <programlisting>
mkdir myspectcl
cp /usr/opt/spectcl/3.3/VMUSBSkel/* myspectcl
            </programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
            The resulting <filename>myspectcl</filename> directory contains
            all the files needed to build a new copy of
            VMUSBSpecTcl and a <filename>Makefile</filename> that actually
            does that.   Since this is just a tailored SpecTcl, you can
            add event processors in the normal way, by writing an
            event processor and registering an instance of it as an event
            processor in <methodname>CreateAnalysisPipeline</methodname>.
        </para>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Using the SpecTcl API to locate parameters by name</title>
            <para>
            If you are writing event processors that create computed parameters,
             you will quickly run into the need to located parameters by name.     
            </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para>
            Specifically, you need to determine if a parameter has been defined by
            the VMUSB unpackers and you need to fetch its value if it has been.
            You may also wish to locate your own parameters by name so that you
            give them values for an event.
        </para>
        <para>
            The example below shows
            an event processor method that looks up two parameters and stores
            their parameter ids in member data of the object. The parameter id
            is the parameter's index into the <parameter>rEvent</parameter> pseudo array
            passed to the event processor's <methodname>operator()</methodname>
            method.
        </para>
    <example>
        <title>Using the SpecTcl API to locate parameters</title>
        <para>
            In the code below, we assume that
            <varname>m_param1, m_param2</varname> and
            <varname>m_initialized</varname> are two integer variables
            and a <type>bool</type> respectively.  We also assume that
            <varname>m_initialized</varname> is set to <literal>false</literal>
            when our event processor is constructed.
        </para>
        <programlisting>
#include &lt;SpecTcl.h&gt;
#include &lt;Parameter.h&gt;
#include &lt;string&gt;
...

//do the actual lookup:

void CMyUnpacker::lookupVariables()
{
    if (!m_initialized) {
        SpecTcl *pApi = SpecTcl::getInstance();  <co id='apilookup-instantiate' />
        
        CParameter* p1 = pApi->findParameter("param1"); <co id='apilookup-p1' />
        if (!p1) {
            throw std::string("Could not find param1"); <co id='apilookup-error' />
        }
        m_param1 = p1->getNumber();            <co id='apilookup-getid' />
        
        CParameter* p2 = pApi->findParameter("param2"); <co id='apilookup-p2' />
        if (!p2) {
            throw std::string("Could not find param2");
        }
        m_param2 = p2->getNumber();
        
        m_initialized = true;
    }
}
        </programlisting>
    </example>
    <calloutlist>
        <callout arearefs='apilookup-instantiate'>
            <para>
                Creates an instance of the SpecTcl API object.  This object
                contains data and methods that make up the SpecTcl API.
            </para>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs='apilookup-p1'>
            <para>
                <methodname>findParameter</methodname> locates the parameter
                object (<type>CParameter</type>) that is associated with a parameter
                given its name. A pointer to the parameter object is returned
                if the parameter is found.  If the parameter does not exist,
                <literal>NULL</literal> is returned.
            </para>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs='apilookup-error' >
            <para>
                In this example, if the named parameter is not found,
                a <type>std::string</type> exception is thrown. You
                must either arrange for the exception to be caught or rely on
                some SpecTcl last chance exception handler.   If this is called
                from an event processor's <methodname>operator()</methodname>
                method, the event processing framework will report the message
                and abort further processing of the event.
            </para>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs='apilookup-getid'>
            <para>
                The <methodname>getNumber</methodname> method of a parameter object
                returns the id of the parameter.  The id of the parameter is
                a unique number that identifies the parameter.  It is als the
                index into the <parameter>rEvent</parameter> array passed to the
                <methodname>operator()</methodname> method of an event processor
                class.
            </para>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs='apilookup-p2'>
            <para>
               Similarly, the code looks up the parameter id of the parameter
               <literal>param2</literal> by locating its <classname>CParameter</classname>
               object and asking it to return the parameter id via
                <methodname>getNumber</methodname>.
            </para>
        </callout>
                    
    </calloutlist>
    
    <para>
        Once this code has executed it sets the <varname>m_initialized</varname>
        member data to <literal>true</literal> so that it only executes once.
        Since parameter definitions tend to change only by recompiling SpecTcl,
        this method is quite safe and has no time impact on event processing.
    </para>
    <para>
        If you are used to using Tree parameters, you can  make use of the
        fact that tree parameter and treeparamter array objects can bind themselves
        to their parameters and then be treated as if they were the parameters
        themselves.  
    </para>
    <para>
        The next example assumes you have the same parameters, <literal>param1</literal>
        and <literal>param2</literal> but that instead of declaring integer
        members you have declared <classname>CTreeParameter</classname> members
        named <varname>m_param1</varname> and <varname>m_param2</varname>.
        Our example will not show how to associate limits, default-binning and
        units with the parameter, however different overloads of the
        <methodname>Initialize</methodname> method can do that if you need that.
    </para>
    <example>
        <title>Binding Tree Parameters to existing parameters</title>
        <programlisting>
#include &lt;TreeParameter.h&gt;
...
void CMyUnpacker::lookupVariables()
{
    if (!m_initialized) {
        m_param1.Initialize("param1");         <co id='tree_init1' />
        m_param1.Bind();                       <co id='tree_bind1' />
        
        m_param2.Initialize("param2");         <co id='tree_2' />
        m_param2.Bind();
        m_initialized = true;    
    }
    
}
        </programlisting>
    </example>
    <calloutlist>
        <callout arearefs='tree_init1'>
            <para>
                A tree parameter declared as
                <programlisting>
<classname>CTreeParameter</classname> <varname> m_param1</varname>;
                </programlisting>
                e.g. is said to be uninitialized. Minimally, this parameter
                must be initialized with the Spectcl parameter name it
                will be used for and bound to that parameter.
            </para>
            <para>
                This line initializes the tree parameter so that it will
                be bound to the parameter <literal>param1</literal>.  
            </para>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs='tree_bind1'>
            <para>
                Binds the parameter.  This looks up the parameter and
                stores the parameter id within the tree parameter object so that
                SpecTcl can know which <literal>rEvent</literal>
                element the tree parameter
                represents, and make that association prior to processing each
                event.
            </para>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs='tree_2'>
            <para>
                The procedure for initializing and binding <varname>m_param2</varname>
                is identical to that of <varname>m_param2</varname>
            </para>
        </callout>
    </calloutlist>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Integrating changes with SpecTcl</title>
        <para>
            The key to VMUSBSpecTcl integration is that it's just SpecTcl.
            Edit the Makefile and add your event processor files to the
            definition of the  <literal>OBJECTS</literal> macro just like you
            would for any other SpecTcl and use <command>make</command>
            to build your SpecTcl.
        </para>
    </formalpara>
    <para>
            If you want to keep your objects separate from the standard
            VMUSBSpecTcl objects you could also do a two levels scheme like
            the one shown below.
    </para>
    <informalexample>
        <programlisting>
            
USEROBJECTS=MyEventProcessor.o
            
OBJECTS=MySpecTclApp.o ParamMapCommand.o CCUSBUnpacker.o \
        CCCUSBPacket.o CPh7xxUnpacker.o CFixedSizedUnpacker.o \
        CC1205Unpacker.o $(USEROBJECTS)
   
        </programlisting>
    </informalexample>
    <para>
        In this scheme you add your objects to a new macro
        <literal>USEROBJECTS</literal> which is invoked at the end of
        <literal>OBJECTS</literal>.
    </para>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Running VMUSBSpecTcl</title>
        <para>
            Beginning with SpecTcl version 3.3-009 VMUSBSpecTcl is installed
            in the <filename>bin</filename> directory of the SpecTcl installation
            tree.  If you don't need to modify it, you can run it directly
            from that location.
        </para>
        <para>
            VMUSBSpecTcl is run just like any other SpecTcl.  Some additions
            to your <filename>SpecTclRC.tcl</filename> file are required
            to load and process your desired configuration file.
            The Tcl code fragment below shows how to do this:
        </para>
        <informalexample>
            <programlisting>
##
# Configure the VM-USB unpacker software:
#
# You should probably change the code below to
# load the configuration file of your choice.
#

set daqconfig [file join ~ config daqconfig.tcl]; # default config file.

lappend auto_path [file join $SpecTclHome TclLibs]
package require vmusbsetup

vmusbConfig $daqconfig

            </programlisting>
        </informalexample>
        <para>
            This example unconditionally uses
            <filename>~/config/daqconfig.tcl</filename> as the configuration filename.
            You should probably substitute some other mechanism.  Two that I have used
            are to
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Remove the definition of daqconfig above and put it
                        in <filename>SpecTclInit.tcl</filename> then you can
                        select a configuration file by editing the relatively short
                        <filename>SpecTclInit.tcl</filename> file.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Set <varname>daqconfig</varname> from a call to
                        <command>tk_getOpenfile</command>.  <command>tk_getOpenFile</command>
                        is a Tk utility that opens a file chooser dialog and
                        returns the path to the file chosen from that
                        dialog.
                        <ulink url='http://www.tcl.tk/man/tcl8.5/TkCmd/getOpenFile.htm' />
                        describes this command and gives an example of its use.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
            To summarize, the key points are that your
            <filename>SpecTclRC.tcl</filename> file should
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Figure out the name of the configuration file you
                    want to use.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Add the SpecTcl Tcl package library directory to the
                    <varname>auto_path</varname>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Load the <literal>vmusbsetup</literal> package via
                    <command>package require</command>
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Invoke the <command>vmusbConfig</command> command passing
                    it the name of your configuration file.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Reference information</title>
        <para>
            This section provides reference information.  It is also used to
            generate manpages for the SpecTcl installation.  The man pages
            are installed in <filename>$SpecTclHome/share/man</filename>
            where <varname>SpecTclHome</varname> is the top level of the
            SpecTcl 3.3 installation tree. You can view these man pages by
            adding the <option>-M $SpecTclHome/share/man</option> option to the
            <command>man</command> command.
        </para>
              <refentry id="vmusb_configfileman">
                <refmeta>
                   <refentrytitle>VMUSB SpecTcl metadata</refentrytitle>
                   <manvolnum>5vmusbSpecTcl</manvolnum>
                </refmeta>
                <refnamediv>
                   <refname>Config File</refname>
                   <refpurpose>VMUSBSpecTcl metadata.</refpurpose>
                </refnamediv>
                
                <refsynopsisdiv>
                  <cmdsynopsis>
                  <command>
set adcChannels(<replaceable>moduleName</replaceable>) <replaceable>channel-list</replaceable>
                  </command>
                  </cmdsynopsis>
        
                </refsynopsisdiv>
                <refsect1>
                   <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
                   <para>
                    The <varname>adcChannels</varname> array is indexed by
                    VMUSB module names and defines the name of SpecTcl parameters
                    into which each module's data will be decoded.
                   </para>
                   <para>
                    For most simple modules, the value of an
                    <varname>adcChannels</varname> element is just the parameter
                    names for each channel of that module.  See SPECIAL CASES
                    below for exceptions.
                   </para>
                   <para>
                    Unused trailing channels can be omitted from the list. By
                    convention, channels that are given the name "" are not
                    used as well.  This allows you to have sparsely populated
                    modules with either trailing unused channels or a set of unused
                    channels in the middle of the module channel list.
                   </para>
                </refsect1>
                <refsect1>
                   <title>
                      SPECIAL CASES
                   </title>
                   <para>
                    Some modules do not fit the model described above in
                    DESCRIPTION.  For these modules, the <varname>adcChannels</varname>
                    array element is still used, however it may be interpreted
                    differently or even coupled with additional metadata.
                   </para>
		   <refsect2>
		     <title>CAEN 785N, 775N, 792N</title>
		     <para>
		       These modules have 16 NIM inputs. While functionally
		       identical to the V785, V775, and V792 modules, only
		       every other ADC channel is routed to the front panel.
		       Therefore when setting up your <varname>adcChannels</varname>
		       array element for these modules you must take this into
		       account for example:
		     </para>
		     <informalexample>
		       <programlisting>
set adcChannels(<replaceable>moduleName</replaceable>)           \
    [list chan0 "" chan1 "" chan2 "" chan3 "" chan4       \
     "" chan5 "" chan6 "" chan7 \
     "" chan8 "" chan9 "" chan10  "" chan11 \
     "" chan12 "" chan13 "" chan14 "" chan15]
		       </programlisting>
		     </informalexample>
		   </refsect2>
                   <refsect2>
                    <title>CAEN Dual range ADC's</title>
                    <para>
                        The CAEN V956 is a dual range QDC.  Each input channel
                        produces a high and a low gain output.  This allows the
                        QDC to have good resolution at both the high and low
                        end of the input range.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        In the CAEN V956, rather than requiring the user to
                        specify each paramter, the value of the parameter list are
                        taken as base parameter names and a
                        <replaceable>base-name</replaceable><literal>.l></literal> and
                        <replaceable>base-name</replaceable><literal>.h</literal> paramter and spectrum
                        are produced for each.  Where <literal>.l</literal> means
                        low range and <literal>.h</literal> means high range.
                        full resolution Spectra are produced for both of these parameters.
                    </para>
                   </refsect2>
                   <refsect2>
                    <title>Washington University HINP chip readout FPGAs</title>
                    <note>
                        <title>NOTE</title>
                        <para>
                            Support for the WUSTL HINP chip readout and analysis
                            was provided by Jon Elson at Washington Univ.
                        </para>
                    </note>
                    <para>
                        Washington University in St. Louis have built front end
                        ASIC based boards that are designed for detector arrays
                        with a large number of channels.
                        The HINP board described in
                        <ulink url='http://www.chemistry.wustl.edu/~lgs/NIMA_573_418_2007.pdf' />
                        use a discriminator and sample and hold array to
                        sparsify and hold peak voltages and timing information
                        from the detector array. 
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The preferred way to acquire data from these boards is
                        via a JTEC XLM-XXV which where the custom firmware in the
                        FPGA sequences analog data through that modules FADC
                        and merges it with the corresponding timing data.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Since essentially arbitrarily sized arrays can be managed
                        with this electronics, additional metadata is required.
                        Specifically, one needs to know the number of HINP chips
                        in the configuration. This information is stored in the
                        array <varname>HINPChips</varname> which is indexed by module
                        name.  Each element of this map is a list of the chip
                        address numbgers of the chips that are being read out.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The <varname>adcChannels</varname> array element is a base
                        name for the entire chipset.  From this base name parameters
                        are constructed for the energy and times of all channels
                        of all chips as follows:
                        <replaceable>base-name</replaceable>.<replaceable>chip-address.nn</replaceable>.<literal>e</literal>
                        and
                        <replaceable>base-name</replaceable>.<replaceable>chip-address</replaceable>.<literal>t</literal>
                        where <replaceable>base-name</replaceable> is the base parameter
                        name from <varname>adcChannels</varname>,
                        <replaceable>chip-address</replaceable> is a two digit
                        decimal chip address from <varname>HINPChips</varname>
                        and <replaceable>nn</replaceable> a two digit channel number
                        from within the chip in the range <literal>[00 .. 15]</literal>.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Full resolution spectra are created for each of these
                        parameters.
                    </para>
                   </refsect2>
                    <refsect2>
                        <title>Washington University PSD chip readout FPGAs</title>
                        <note>
                            <title>NOTE</title>
                            <para>
                                Support for the WUSTL PSD chip readout and analysis
                                was provided by Jon Elson at Washington Univ.
                            </para>
                        </note>

                        <para>
                            Washington University in St. Louis has built a
                            set of front end board for large detector arrays.
                            The board are populated with a set of ASIC chip boards.
                            Each ASIC is capabile of performing charge integration
                            over three regions of the pulse.
                            See
                            <ulink url="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0168900209019639" />
                            for information about this system, althought the
                            channel density has been increased to 16 channels/chip
                            since that article was published.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            The analog are sparsified and held in the ASIC
                            along with timing information for the non-zero
                            channels.  The preferred way to read data from
                            from the PSD chips is with a JTEC XLM-XXV.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            Custom firmware in the XLM's FPGA sequences analog
                            data to the FADC on the XLM-XXV and combines it with
                            the digital timing information for each non-zero
                            channel.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            Since arbitrary sized arrays can be handled by
                            this system, the <varname>adcChannels</varname>
                            variable only supplies a parameter base name.
                            Additional metadata is required to describe the
                            size of the system.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            <varname>PSDChips</varname>
                            is an array that is indexed by module name and
                            contains a list of the chip addresses that are in
                            use by the system.  Each chip is capable of
                            handling 16 channels.  Therefore, the base name
                            and chip addresses are used to create parameter names
                            of the form:
                            <replaceable>base-name</replaceable>.abct.<replaceable>chip-address</replaceable>.<replaceable>nn</replaceable>
                            Where; <replaceable>base-name</replaceable> is the
                            value in <varname>adcChannels</varname> for the module,
                            <literal>abct</literal> is one of a,b,c,t where
                            a,b,c represent an integrationinterval and t the time
                            parameter.  <replaceable>chip-address</replaceable> is the
                            address of the chip and <replaceable>nn</replaceable> the
                            two digit channel number within the chip from
                            <literal>[0..15]</literal>.
                        </para> 
                    </refsect2>
                    <refsect2>
                        <title>Indiana University MASE chip readout FPGAs</title>
                        <para>
                            The Indiana University MASE chip readout is a hieararchical
                            readout system intended for highly segmented silicon
                            detector arrays.  It is described in
                            <ulink url='http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0168900206016664' />.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            In summary, the system consists of a number
                            of Controller boards (COBs).  A number of
                            Channel boards (CHB) connect to these COBs.
                            Each channel board can manage 16 channels.
                            The entire system i scapable of reading
                            over 4000 channels of Si detector. The entire system
                            is read using an FPGA base XLM module.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            In addition to <varname>adcChannels</varname> the
                            MASE requires two piecs of additional metadata.
                            <varname>maseCOBCount</varname> is an array indexed
                            by module name that contains the number of COB boards
                            in the system.  the array <varname>maseCHBCounts</varname>
                            further provides a list of the number of CHB modules
                            attached to each COB. This allows for COBs that are not
                            fully populated.  CHB addresses are always sequential
                            and start from zero as are COB adresses.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            As the MASE system only produces energy information,
                            this results in parameters and full resolution spectra
                            of with names of the form:
                            <replaceable>base-name</replaceable>.<replaceable>cob</replaceable>.<replaceable>chb</replaceable>.<replaceable>chan</replaceable>
                            Where <replaceable>base-name</replaceable> is the
                            base name of the parameter in <varname>adcChannels</varname>,
                            <replaceable>cob</replaceable> is the COB board
                            address as a two digit decimal number,
                            <replaceable>chb</replaceable> is the CHB board
                            address as a two digit decimal number and
                            <replaceable>chan</replaceable> is a two digit
                            channel number within the CHB.
                        </para> 
                    </refsect2>
                    <refsect2>
                        <title>CAEN V977 I/O register</title>
                        <para>
                            The CAEN V977 operates like a 'normal' one channel
                            module except that the spectrum it generates is
                            a 16bit bitmask spectrum.
                        </para>
                    </refsect2>
                    <refsect2>
                        <title>CAEN V 1x90 multi-hit TDCs</title>
                        <para>
                            The CAEN V 1x90 TDC family (V 1190 and V1290) are
                            multihit TDCs that have settablechannel ranges.
                            The configuration parameters also make it possible
                            to know the timescale of the spectra created for this
                            module. Furthermore, since the module gate is clocked in
                            by the TDC timing relative to that gate is much worse
                            than the TDC is capabile.  Therefore the software supports
                            doing a digital subtraction from the digitized time of the
                            gate (a reference channel).
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            The additional metadata for this module is therefore
                            the values of the following options:
                        </para>
                        <variablelist>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>-depth</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        Determines the number of hits that will
                                        be histogrammed.  The software will
                                        create one histogram per channel per allowed hit.
                                        Names of the parameters/histograms
                                        are of the form <replaceable>name</replaceable>.<replaceable>n</replaceable>
                                        where <replaceable>name</replaceable> was the
                                        name for the channel in <varname>adcChannels</varname>
                                        and <replaceable>n</replaceable> is the
                                        hit number from zero.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>-refchannel</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        Set the channel number that will be used
                                        as  the gate time channel.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>-channelcount</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        The V1x90 is a familly of TDCs with many
                                        different options for channel count.
                                        This value determines the number of
                                        channels to expect.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>-window</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        Determines the full scale range of the TDC
                                        by setting the width of the digitized time
                                        window.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>-offset</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        Determines where the window starts relative to the
                                        gate and therefore establishes the time at the
                                        left end of the spectrum.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>-edgeresolution</option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        Determines the width in time of each
                                        channel of the spectrum.  Together with
                                        <option>-window</option> this also
                                        determines the number of channels
                                        in each spectrum.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                        </variablelist>
                        <para>
                            Note that setting all but <option>-channelcountM</option>,
                            <option>-refchannel</option> and <option>-depth</option>
                            affect the way the TDC operates and you should keep
                            your application in mind when doing so.
                        </para>
                    </refsect2>
                </refsect1>
        
              </refentry>
              
        
    </chapter>
</book>
